またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
どこだ どこへ行った
Where is she?
Where did she go?
やつは あの女は
Where is she? Where is that woman?
Where is she? Where did she go?
どこだ どこへ行った
Where did that woman go?
あの女は どこへ行った
The Cat and The Book of Friends
If you want a part-time job, then you should work at the beach! At a beach house!
バイトなら 海だろ 海の家
Ah, the beach, huh?
おお 海か
なんか出会いとかあったりして
Maybe I'll meet someone.
ある ある 絶対
That could happen! It'll happ—
あれ 夏目 何やってんだ お前
Natsume?
What are you doing?
何って
What am I doing?
なんでもない
Nothing.
Nothing?
なんでもないって 泥だらけじゃないかよ 大丈夫か
You're all muddy.
Are you okay?
Yeah.
な 近くに神社はないか
Hey, is there a shrine nearby?
I think there's a shrine once you pass through those bushes there.
神社なら その藪を抜けたところに確か
Thanks.
ありがとう
おい 夏目 何だあいつ
Hey, Natsume!
What's up with him?
何急いでんだ
Why's he in such a hurry?
何だ 今の
What was that?
すんげえ風
That was some crazy wind.
He's a strange guy, huh?
あいつ変わってるよな
He hasn't talked much ever since he transferred.
転入してきてからちゃんと喋ったこと殆どないもんな
He's kind of hard to talk to.
なんか話かけづらいっていうかさ
"What are you doing," huh?
何やってんだ か
I'm jealous that you can't see them.
あれが見えないなんて 羨ましいよ
Wait!
待て
Ever since I was small, I would sometimes see strange things.
小さな頃から 時々変なものを見た
They were probably the ones called Youkai.
それは恐らく妖怪と言われるものの類
元々いい気はしなかったが
They were never really friendly,
ここに引越してきてから
but ever since I moved here,
やたらと絡んでくるやつがいて困っている
there have been some who randomly pick fights, and it's been quite problematic.
そういう時は 神社にでも逃げ込んでしまえば
When that happens, and if I run away to a shrine—
捕まえた
I've got you.
やっと捕まえたぞ レイコ
I've finally got you, Reiko!
レイコ？
Reiko?
Now, return it.
さあ 返せ
さあ さあ
Come now, return it!
Wait.
待て まあ待て
Just wait, it'll be a bother if your name is called.
お前の名前が呼ばれては厄介だ
Pull out her tongue so that she can't call your name.
名前を呼ばれないよう舌を抜いてしまおう
Her tongue?
舌を
い いてえ
That hurts!
Ow!
痛い 痛い
Fool, she got away!
ばか 逃げたぞ
痛い 痛いよ
Cursed human!
おのれ
どうして いつも
Why does this always happen?
見たくて見てる訳じゃないのに
It's not like I want to see them.
あら 貴志君
Ah, Takashi-kun?
We only need three plates.
お皿は三枚でいいのよ
え でもそこにいるお客さんの分
But...
We need one for our guest over there.
The child was saying some strange things again today.
あの子 また今日変なこと言ったのよ
He just wants attention. He's lonely.
気を引きたいんだよ
寂しいのさ
You think so?
そうなのかしら なんだか気味が悪いわ
He's kind of creepy.
ほら あそこだよ
Look, right over there.
Where?
どこに
なにもいないわよ 貴志君
There's nothing there, Takashi-kun.
Something is  there! Look carefully!
いるよ よく見てよ
Look, right over there!
ほら あそこだよ
あそこだよ
It's right there! It's looking right at us.
こっち見てるじゃない
いるってば いるんだよ
It's there!
It's really there...
I'm sorry, I can't see it.
御免ね 見えないわ
いっててて…
これ まさか？
Don't tell me this is a...
ああ 破れた
It's been broken.
The barrier that sealed me has been broken!
我を封じし結界が破れたぞ
Barrier?
結界？ やばい
Oh, no!
I-It's not working...
駄目だ どうしよう
What should I do?
人のくせいに私を見て動じないとは 生意気な
You're quite a precious human, to not bumble at the sight of me!
Say something.
何か言え
慣れているんでね
I'm used to it.
ふん ふてぶてしいやつめ
Impudent brat.
おや お前 夏目レイコじゃないか
Oh?
Aren't you Natsume Reiko?
I've got you, Reiko!
捕まえたぞ レイコ
レイコ
Reiko...
なんだ 違うのか
What? You're not?
Natsume Reiko was my grandmother's name.
夏目レイコは祖母の名だ
祖母？ なんだお前はレイコの孫か
Grandmother? What, you're her grandson?
I see. If I look carefully, you're a man.
なるほど よく見れば男だ
よく見なくても男だよ
You don't need to look carefully to discern that I'm a man.
Unlike humans, we do not particularly concern ourselves with gender.
人間と違ってな
我々は性別などはさほど頓着せんのだ
祖母知ってるのか
You knew my grandmother?
あぁ この近くに住んでいてな
Yes, she lived near here.
She was quite the beautiful human.
それはそれは美しい人間だった
And just like you, she was able to see Ayakashi.
そしてお前えのように妖ものを見ることができた
However, the humans around her could not.
だが周りの人間が見えない
誰もレイコのことが理解できなかった
No one was able to understand Reiko.
She was always alone.
レイコはいつも一人だった
いつもいつも一人だった
She was always, always alone.
Alone...
一人…
そこで レイコは妖ものを相手にし始めた
And so...
Reiko began to confront the Ayakashi.
友人帳を知っているかい
Do you know of the Book of Friends?
The Book of Friends?
友人帳？
あ そういえば 祖母の…
Oh yeah, it was my grandmother's...
消えた
He vanished.
あら お帰り 貴志君
Oh, welcome back, Takashi-kun.
塔子さん ただいま
Touko-san, I'm home.
どうしたの 顔が青いわよ
What's wrong? Your face is all pale.
どこか悪いの
Are you feeling sick?
ああ いえ 大丈夫です
Ah, no, I'm fine.
まあ 制服どろどろじゃないの
Your uniform is all muddy.
何があったの
What happened?
No, I just fell.
いや これは転んだだけで
転んだ？ どこで？ 怪我はないの？ 痛い所は？
Fell? Where?
Are you injured? Does it hurt anywhere?
うん 大丈夫です
I'm fine. Sorry for making you worry.
すいません 心配掛けちゃって
本当大丈夫ですから
I'm really fine.
それならいいけど
That's good, then.
何があったら遠慮しないで言ってよ
If something happens, just tell me. You don't need to hold back.
Okay, thank you.
はい ありがとうございます
わんぱくも結構だけど 程程にね
Being naughty is fine, but keep it to a minimum, okay?
はい
Okay.
妖怪に追いかけられたなんて塔子さんには言えないからな
I can't tell Touko-san that I was being chased by Youkai.
気味の悪い思いはさせたくない
I don't want her to be creeped out.
両親を早くに無くした俺は 親戚の家を転々としてきた
Having lost my parents early, I moved from place to place among my relatives.
血の繋がっていない
We weren't related by blood.
But I have been living with people who are somehow connected to me.
でも俺と関わりを持ってしまった人々の間で 俺は暮らしてきた
この家のお世話になり始めたのは先月
I began to live in this house last month.
ここはかつて俺の祖母も暮らした土地だ
My grandmother also lived on this land once.
She passed away, but like me, she had the power to see things that others couldn't.
亡くなった祖母も俺と同じように
他の人には見えないものを見てしまう力を持っていて
そのせいで 周りから疎まれていたという
And because of it, she was shunned by others.
I'm sure it's somewhere among the things I inherited...
もらった遺品の中に確か…
これか 招き猫が言ってたの
Is this what that fortune cat was talking about?
What is this?
なんなんだ これ
それを渡せ
Hand that over.
That's not something you should have.
それは お前の持つべきものではない
Hand it over...
友人帳を 寄越せ
The Book of Friends!
Takashi-kun! What was that sound just now?
貴志君 今の音は 何
S-Sorry, it was nothing!
すいません なんでもないでーす
Really?
そう ちょっとお買い物行ってくるから お留守番お願いね
I'm going shopping for a bit, so watch the house, okay?
Okay, take care!
はい 行ってらっしゃい
抜けん 早く 私を出せ
Hurry up and let me out!
Ah, give me the Book of Friends too!
友人帳も出せ
Ah, no, no, no! Let me out first!
いやいや でもまず私先をに出せ
Hand me the Book of Friends after that!
その後に 友人帳も
I guess I'll leave him alone for a bit.
しばらくほっとくか
Leave after you eat that.
それ食ったら帰れよ
You freeload here?
お前ここの居候か
Shut up, you're just a cat.
うるさいな ニャンコのくせいに
What do you mean, "Cat"? How rude!
ニャンコとはなんだ 失敬な
This fortune cat form is not my true form!
この招き猫は本来の私の姿ではない
My true form is quite elegant!
本来の私は それはそれは優美な姿なのだ
じゃ ニャンコじゃないのか
You're not a cat, then?
That's what I'm telling you.
だから そう言ってるだろう
ニャン ニャン
You are a cat.
ニャンコじゃないのか
N-N-No!
ち…違うわ
My body is just used to this form!
体がこの形に慣れてしまっただけだ
Well, whatever. Just eat that quickly and leave.
まあ何でもいいから 早く食って帰ってくれ
I don't want any trouble.
面倒は御免だから
No, I won't leave.
いや 帰らん
I know you have the Book of Friends.
お前が友人帳を持っていることが分かったからな
I also owe you for breaking the barrier.
結界を破ってもらった恩義もある
I'll be your bodyguard from now on, so call me "sensei."
これからはお前の用心棒をしてやるから
先生とでも呼ぶんだな
Bodyguard?
用心棒って？ そんなに危険なものなのか
Is this that dangerous?
What, you don't know anything?
なんだ 何もしらんのか
Within the Book of Friends are the names of the Ayakashi that Natsume Reiko defeated.
友人帳にはな
夏目レイコが負かした妖もの達の名前が書いてあるのだよ
Names?
名前？
Reiko challenged the Ayakashi she met, one after the other.
レイコは出会う妖ものたちに次々と勝負を挑んだ
Since she was born with immense spiritual power, she was undefeated.
生まれながらにして強力な妖力を持つレイコは全戦全勝
そして負けたものには
And those who lost
were made to write their names on paper as proof of their subordination.
子分となる証しとして紙に名を書かせた
The Book of Friends is composed of those who wrote their names.
それをつづりにしたものが友人帳なのだ
So they're the names of Youkai?
妖怪の名前だったのか
It is said that they cannot defy
その契約書を持つものに名を呼ばれると
the one who holds the contracts and calls their names.
逆らうことはできないと言われている
Basically, if you have the Book of Friends,
つまり 友人帳を手に入れると
you are able to control the Ayakashi linked with the names in it.
名を連ねた妖ものたちを統べることをできてしまうのだ
な 危険だろう
See? Dangerous, isn't it?
A seed.
種 ついてるぞ 口の横
It's stuck beside your mouth.
I see. So that's why you want this, Nyanko-sensei.
なるほどね それでニャンコ先生はこれを欲しがった訳だ
Ah, you idiot! Don't treat it so carelessly!
ばか ぞんざいに扱うな
It is said that if you damage the characters, you'll hurt the one who has the name as well!
文字が傷つくと名を持ちものも傷つくと言われているのだ
あ そうなんだ
Oh, really?
あれ ってことは
Then does that mean you're in this too?
ニャンコ先生もこれに載ってるのか
Like heck I am!
載っ取ろうわ
I'm just telling you how delicate it is!
それだけデリケートな代物だといっておるのだ
Really?
本当に
What's with those eyes?
何だその目は 私がレイコごときに負けるものか
Do you think I'd lose to someone like Reiko?
Weren't you sealed away, though?
でも封印されてたじゃないか
A-A-Ah, well, there are some meaningful reasons for that.
あ…あれ にはなあ また色々と深い訳があって
No! More importantly,
いや そんなことよりもだ
the Book of Friends' power is much more immense than you imagine.
お前が考えているより 友人帳の力は遥かに大きい
That's why the Ayakashi with their names in it are desperately searching for Natsume Reiko.
だからこそ そこに名をつられたあやかし者達は
必死に夏目レイコを探しているのだ
お前 危ないぞ
You're in danger.
Hello?
御免下さい
C-Coming!
はい
Hello?
ごめん下さい
Sorry, the person living here is away now.
すいません 家のものは今留守でして
So, you are here.
やはり 帰ってきたね レイコ
You came back, Reiko.
Hand me the Book of Friends!
渡せ 友人帳を
Hello?
ごめん下さい
You... Return it!
返せ
Ah, geez...
Nyanko-sensei!
ニャンコ先生
Where are you planning to go?
どこへ行く気だ
どこへって
Where?
Hide in that bush.
その物陰に隠れろ
Damn...
まいったな
It's not something a human can manage.
人の手におえるものではないわ
You understand well now, don't you?
さ よく分かったろう
So, give it to me!
だから 私に送り
No.
駄目だ
な…何故だ
Why? You're just a human. Do you plan to supersede the Ayakashi?
人間のくせに妖ものの上に立つつもりか
そんな訳ないだろう
Of course not.
Then what? What other purpose is there besides that for you?
じゃ なんだ
お前にとってそう使う以外何の意味がある
It doesn't concern you.
先生には関係ないだろう
I planned to wait until you changed your mind, but forget that.
脈あるまでと思ってやったが 友人帳を寄越せ
Hand over the Book of Friends!
だ…駄目だ 先生こそ変なことに使う気だろう
N-No.
You're the one who's going to use it for bad things, aren't you?
Of course! It's such an interesting object.
当たり前だ そんな面白そうなもの
You're terrible...
なんてやつだ
Hurry up and hand it over!
早く渡せ さもないと 潰してしまうぞ
If you don't, I'll crush you!
This is...
これは 友人帳はな
The Book of Friends is...
It's an important inheritance from my grandmother.
俺にとって祖母の大事な遺品なんだよ
It's true that she couldn't get along with other people.
確かに 祖母は人とうまく付き合えなかったらしい
There are barely any people that remember her.
覚えている人も殆どいないんだ
She died young,
彼女は若くして亡くなったから
だから 唯一血縁の俺ぐらいは繋がりを持っていてやりたいんだ
so as her only blood relative, I want to hold on to our link and do it.
I can't think of it as another person's problem.
人事とは思えないしな
Hey, I want to return them, so what should I do?
な 先生 返したいんだけど
どうしたらいいのかな
Return them?
返す？
名前だよ 妖怪達に返してやりたいんだ
The names. I want to give them back to the Youkai.
Fool. Don't do it, it's a waste.
あほ やめろ もったいない
Plus, there are some evil ones in there.
それに中には凶暴なやつも多い
No matter how many lives you might have, it won't be enough.
命がいくつあっても足りんぞ
I'll be fine.
平気だよ 俺には先生がついてるじゃないか
You're with me, sensei.
I want to do what Reiko-san left undone.
レイコさんがやり残したことを俺がやりたいんだよ
If I die along the way, then you can have the Book of Friends.
もし俺が途中で命を落としたら
友人帳は譲る
Lend me your power, sensei.
力を貸してくれよ 先生
Natsume, can I really have the Book of Friends when you're gone?
夏目 お前が消える時
本当に友人帳をもらっていいんだな
Yeah, sure.
ああ いいよ
Very well, I will witness it myself.
よかろう 見届けよう
ありがとう
Thank you.
Damn Reiko! I'll pull her tongue out!
おのれ レイコ 舌を抜いてくれるわ
You're...
お前は？
You want the Book of Friends?
友人帳が欲しいのか
ふん 友人帳さえあれば この辺りの主になれる
Once I have the Book of Friends, I'll be the master of this area!
Isn't that what you want too, Madara?
お前もそうなんだろう 斑
Don't lump me together with you, you vulgar bastard.
一緒にするな 低級めが
Cursed fool!
おのれ
First, you imagine their form,
まずは相手の姿をイメージしつつ 開き 念じろ
open the book, and then pray.
One who would protect me, show your name!
我を護りしものよ その名を示せ
Get lost and never appear before me again!
うせろ そして二度と我が前に姿を現すな
Is this it?
これか
次に必要なのは
What you need next is Reiko's saliva and breath.
レイコの唾液と息
As her blood relative, you can do it.
血縁のお前ならやれる
契約書を破ってくわえ
Tear out the contract and bite on it.
Put you hands together with force and concentrate.
両の手を強く打ち合わせ 集中し
And then, blow a whiff.
ふっと息を吐く
I'm lonely...
寂しい 寂しい
I'm hungry...
おなかがすいた
ああ わしの饅頭
My steamed bun!
It's not that good.
あんまり美味しくないわよ これ
What are you doing, you human?
人間のくせに何をする 意地汚い
Your spirit is filthy!
If you want some good steamed buns,
then I recommend the ones from Nanatsuji.
美味しいお饅頭が食べたかったら 七辻屋のがお勧めよ
Nanatsuji?
七辻？
I know, if you fight with me and you win,
そうね あたしと勝負してあなたが勝てたら
I'll treat you to some food.
ご馳走してあげましょうか
You can see me?
お前 私が見えるんだな
Yeah, I can see you.
ええ 見えるわよ
Aren't you scared?
恐ろしくはないのか
Not at all!
全然 だって私は強いもの
Because I'm strong!
Let's start now.
じゃ いくわよ
ああ 痛い
All right, it's my win!
はい 私の勝ち
Wasn't that a surprise attack?
不意打ちじゃないか
A win is a win.
勝ちは勝ちよ
All right, now you're one of my followers.
よし これであなたは私の子分よ
Followers?
子分？
何？
What?
What's with that injury on your cheek?
その頬の傷はどうした
ああ 石をぶつけられてね
Someone threw a rock at me.
They said I was creepy.
私は気味が悪いんですって
Hey, you have a pretty name.
へー あなた 綺麗な名前なのね
子分になったんだら
You're my follower now,
so when I call your name, you have to come flying to me.
この名前を呼んだら飛んできてよね
What's your name?
お前の名前は
It's Reiko.
レイコよ
レイコ
Reiko...
See you later.
じゃ まったねー
Reiko...
レイコ…レイコ…
ああ 今日も呼ばないのかい
She won't call me today either?
It's lonely! A lot more than before!
寂しい 前よりずっと
Return it! Return my name!
返せ 名前を返せ
No matter how long I wait, you never call my name!
どんなに待っても 呼んでくれないくらいなら
Hishigaki...
ひしがき
Reiko...
レイコ もういいのかい
Is it okay now?
Are you okay by yourself now?
もう一人でも平気かい
I'm sure my grandmother wasn't alone.
祖母はきっと 一人じゃなかったよ
Thank you, Hishigaki,
ありがとう ひしがき 心優しい祖母の友人
my dear grandmother's kind-hearted friend.
Did you see Reiko?
レイコには会えたかい
Yeah.
She was a mean person, wasn't she?
ひどいやつだったろう
Do you think you can do it, Natsume?
やれるかい 夏目
I want to do it.
俺はやりたい
I see.
そうか
As usual, I can't come to like the Youkai.
妖怪のことは 相変わらず 好きにはなれない
But...
でも
Sensei, they say the steamed buns there are good.
先生 あそこの饅頭うまいんだってさ
What? Let's go eat them!
何 GOGO
Hey, don't be so wild!
こら 暴れるな
Whether good or bad, it was a meeting.
良くも悪くも 出会いの一つ
Huh? Can cats eat sweet things?
あれ でもニャンコって甘いもの食べてもいいのか
I told you, I'm not a cat!
だから ニャンコじゃないと言ってるだろうか
Some steamed buns, please!
饅頭ください
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
The Dew God's Small Shrine
What is your name?
君の名は？
I am the Dew God.
私は露神
Hey, that lady is worshiping at your shrine.
おい ばあさんがお前の祠拝んでるぞ
I've always watched her and listened to her voice.
私はあの人をずっと見てきた
声を聞いてきた
ああ 私の声が聞こえたらな
If only she could hear my voice.